<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><plecoflash formatversion="2" creator="Pleco User -1" generator="Pleco 2.0 Flashcard Exporter" platform="Android" created="1781333520"><cards><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">私</headword><headword charset="tc">私</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">si1</pron><cantopron type="yyjp" tones="numbers">si1</cantopron><defn>adjective 1 personal; private (opp. 公) 私信 sīxìn personal (or private) letter 2 selfish (opp. 公) 無私 wúsī selfless 私字當頭 sīzìdāngtóu make self-interest the first consideration 3 secret; private 私話 sīhuà confidential talk 4 illicit; illegal 私刻公章 sī kè gōngzhāng illicitly engrave an official seal 私賣違禁品 sīmài wéijìnpǐn illicit sale of contraband goods 
noun 1 private (or selfish) interest; selfish motive (or idea) (opp. 公) 2 contraband; smuggled (or contrabanded) goods See 37005056走私zou3si1走私</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="30756864"/><catassign category="BotG-Ep2"/><catassign category="BotG-Ep3-Ep6"/><catassign category="1,2,3"/><catassign category="IAmMichael"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">歳</headword><headword charset="tc">歳</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">sui4</pron><defn>year; age; harvest</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PUNI" entryid="27507"/><catassign category="IAmMichael"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">仕</headword><headword charset="tc">仕</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shi4</pron><cantopron type="yyjp" tones="numbers">si6</cantopron><defn>verb be an official; fill an office 出仕 chūshì take up an official post; become an official See 33760768學而優則仕xue2er2you1ze2shi4學而優則仕 
noun chess bodyguard, one of the pieces in Chinese chess</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="30195712"/><catassign category="IAmMichael"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">事</headword><headword charset="tc">事</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">shi4</pron><cantopron type="yyjp" tones="numbers">si6</cantopron><defn>noun 1 matter; affair; thing; business 國家大事 guójiā dàshì state affairs 這事兒不好辦。 zhè shì r bù hǎobàn. This matter is hard to manage. 這是怎麼回事兒？ Zhè shì zěnme huí shì r? What’s this all about? or What’s happening? 2 trouble; accident 出事 chūshì meet with a mishap; have an accident 3 job; work 她找到事兒了。 Tā zhǎo dào shìr le. She’s got a job. or She’s found a job. 4 responsibility; involvement 沒你的事。 Méi nǐ de shì. It’s none of your business. 這件案子裡還有他的事兒呢。 Zhè jiàn ànzi lǐ hái yǒu tā deshì r ne. He was involved in this case too. 有我什麼事兒, 幹嗎怪我？ Yǒu wǒ shénmeshì r, gànmá guài wǒ? I had nothing to do with it, so why blame me? 
verb literary 1 wait upon; serve 事父母 shì fùmǔ wait upon one’s parents 2 be engaged in 不事營生 bù shì yíngsheng lead an idle life</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="30215936"/><catassign category="IAmMichael"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">学校</headword><headword charset="tc">學校</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xue2xiao4</pron><cantopron type="yyjp" tones="numbers">hok6 haau6</cantopron><defn>noun school; educational institution 高等學校 gāoděng xuéxiào institution of higher learning 師範學校 shīfàn xuéxiào teachers’ (or normal) school 專業學校 zhuānyè xuéxiào specialized (or vocational) school</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="33775360"/><catassign category="IAmMichael"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">先生</headword><headword charset="tc">先生</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">xian1sheng5</pron><cantopron type="yyjp" tones="numbers">sin1 saang1</cantopron><defn>noun 1 teacher 要做人民的先生, 先做人民的學生。 Yào zuò rénmín de xiānsheng, xiān zuò rénmín de xuésheng. To be a teacher of the people, one must first be their pupil. 2 Mister (Mr); gentleman; sir 總統先生 Zǒngtǒng xiānsheng Mr President 女士們, 先生們！ Nǚshì men, xiānsheng men! Ladies and Gentlemen! 3 husband 她先生出差去了。 Tā xiānsheng chūchāi qù le. Her husband is away on business. 我先生不在家。 Wǒ xiānsheng bù zàijiā. My husband is out. 4 dialect doctor 5 dated [usu. after a profession] 算命先生 suànmìng xiānsheng fortune-teller 賬房先生 zhàngfángxiānsheng bookkeeper</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="32872960"/><catassign category="IAmMichael"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">家族</headword><headword charset="tc">家族</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">jia1zu2</pron><cantopron type="yyjp" tones="numbers">gaa1 zuk6</cantopron><defn>noun clan; family</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="23658496"/><catassign category="IAmMichael"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">母</headword><headword charset="tc">母</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">mu3</pron><cantopron type="yyjp" tones="numbers">mou5</cantopron><defn>noun 1 mother 母女 mǔ-nǚ mother and daughter 老母 lǎomǔ one’s old mother 2 one&apos;s female elders 伯母 bómǔ aunt; wife of father’s elder brother 祖母 zǔmǔ (paternal) grandmother 3 female (animal) (opp. 公) 母狼 mǔláng she-wolf 母象 mǔxiàng female elephant 你的狗是公的還是母的？ Nǐ de gǒu shì gōng de háishi mǔ de？ Is your dog male or female? 4 nut (so called because of the female screw thread) 螺母 luómǔ (screw) nut 5 origin; parent 母結構 mǔ jiégòu parent structure</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="27046400"/><catassign category="IAmMichael"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">妹</headword><headword charset="tc">妹</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">mei4</pron><cantopron type="yyjp" tones="numbers">mui6</cantopron><defn>noun 1 younger sister; sister 她是我小妹。 Tā shì wǒ xiǎo mèi. She’s my youngest sister. 2 junior female relative of the same generation 表妹 biǎomèi (female) cousin 3 dialect young girl 打工妹 dǎgōngmèi young woman migrant worker from rural villages</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="26666240"/><catassign category="IAmMichael"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">家</headword><headword charset="tc">家</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">jia1</pron><cantopron type="yyjp" tones="numbers">gaa1</cantopron><defn>noun 1 family; household 張家和王家 Zhāng jiā hé wáng jiā the Zhangs and the Wangs 他全家都是工人。 Tā quánjiā dōu shì gōngrén. They’re all workers in his family. 小區裡家家都愛養花。 Xiǎoqū lǐ jiājiā dōu ài yǎnghuā. In this neighbourhood, every family loves growing flowers. 2 home 回家 huíjiā go home 不在家 bù zàijiā not be in; be out 上我家去吧。 Shàng wǒ jiā qù ba. Come to my place. 3 person or family engaged in a certain trade 船家 chuánjiā boatman 4 specialist in a certain field 畫家 huàjiā painter 科學家 kēxuéjiā scientist 5 school of thought 儒家 Rújiā Confucian school 6 self-deprecating my [in speaking of relatives older than oneself] See 23637248家父jia1fu4家父 7 (in playing cards, mah-jong, etc.) party; side See 59564771對家dui4jia1對家;29587456上家shang4jia1上家;36692480莊家zhuang1jia5莊家 
adjective domestic; tamed (opp. 野) 家兔 jiātù rabbit 
measure word [for families or business establishments] 兩家人家 Liǎng jiā rénjia two families 三家商店 sān jiā shāngdiàn three shops 一家電影院 yī jiā diànyǐngyuàn a cinema</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="23631104"/><catassign category="IAmMichael"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">映</headword><headword charset="tc">映</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ying4</pron><cantopron type="yyjp" tones="numbers">jing2</cantopron><defn>verb reflect; mirror; shine 他的臉被爐火映得通紅。 Tā de liǎn bèi lúhuǒ yìng de tōnghóng. His cheeks shone red before the glowing oven. 朝霞映在湖面上。 Zhāoxiá yìng zài húmiàn shàng. The glory of the dawn is mirrored on the lake.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="34883584"/><catassign category="IAmMichael"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">画</headword><headword charset="tc">畫</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">hua4</pron><cantopron type="yyjp" tones="numbers">waak6</cantopron><defn>noun 1 drawing; painting; picture 畫風 huàfēng style of painting 一張畫 yī zhāng huà a picture 2 decorated with paintings or pictures 畫船 huà chuán gaily-painted boat 
verb draw; paint 畫一個圈 Huà yī ge quān draw (or describe) a circle 畫一張草圖 huà yī zhāng cǎotú make a sketch; sketch 
noun 1 stroke (of a Chinese character) “人”字有兩畫。 “rén” zì yǒu liǎng huà. The character 人 is made up of two strokes. 2 dialect horizontal stroke (in Chinese characters) 一畫 Yī huà a horizontal stroke 
verb draw; mark; sign 比畫 bǐhuà gesture; gesticulate See 62339299畫線hua4xian4畫線</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="22946304"/><catassign category="IAmMichael"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">料理</headword><headword charset="tc">料理</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">liao4li3</pron><cantopron type="yyjp" tones="numbers">liu6 lei5</cantopron><defn>verb 1 arrange; manage; attend to; take care of 料理後事 liàolǐ hòushì make arrangements for a funeral 料理家務 Liàolǐ jiāwù manage household chores 料理自己的生活 liàolǐ zìjǐ de shēnghuó take care of oneself 2 dated cook; prepare food 
noun cooking; cuisine; dish 日本料理 Rìběn liàolǐ Japanese cuisine</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="25884928"/><catassign category="IAmMichael"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">好</headword><headword charset="tc">好</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">hao3</pron><cantopron type="yyjp" tones="numbers">hou2</cantopron><defn>adjective 1 good; fine; nice (opp. 壞) 好人 hǎorén nice person 祖國的好兒子 Zǔguó de hǎo érzi worthy (or fine) son of our country 莊稼長得真好。 Zhuāngjia zhǎng de zhēn hǎo. The crops are growing well. 2 friendly; kind 好朋友 Hǎo péngyou good (or great) friend 他們對我真好。 Tāmen duì wǒ zhēn hǎo. They are really kind to me. 倆孩子又好了。 Liǎ háizi yòu hǎo le. The two children are friends again. 3 be in good health; get well 你好哇！ Nǐ hǎo wa! How are you? 我的病好了。 Wǒ de bìng hǎo le. I’m well (or all right) now. 4 be ready; done 飯好了。 Fàn hǎo le. The food (or rice) is ready. 5 [after verbs to indicate finishing or finishing satisfactorily] 我把他的病治好了。 Wǒ bǎ tā de bìng zhì hǎo le. I cured his illness. 這件事他做不好。 Zhè jiàn shì tā zuò bù hǎo. He can’t do this job well. 坐好吧, 要開會了。 Zuò hǎo ba, yào kāihuì le. Take your seats, please. The meeting is going to begin. 6 [before verbs to denote what is satisfying] good; easy 好吃 hǎochī good to eat—delicious 暖瓶放在這兒好拿。 Nuǎnpíng fàng zài zhèr hǎo ná. It’s handy to have the thermos here. 這本書可不好買。 Zhè běn shū kě bù hǎo mǎi. This book is not easily available. 這個問題好回答。 Zhège wèntí hǎo huídá. This question is easy to answer. 7 [at the beginning of a sentence or clause, to express agreement, disapproval, surprise, etc.] 好, 就這麼辦。 Hǎo, jiù zhème bàn. OK, it’s settled. 好了, 不要再說了。 Hǎo le, bùyào zài shuō le. All right, no need to say any more. 好！ 那得多少錢！ Hǎo! Nà dé duōshao qián! Gosh! How much money will that cost! 好,  這下可麻煩了。 Hǎo, zhè xià kě máfan le. Well, we’re in for trouble now. 
adverb 1 [before adjectives with exclamatory force] very; quite; so 好大的工程！ Hǎo dà de gōngchéng! What a huge project! 你好大膽子。 Nǐ hǎo dà dǎnzi. You are so daring. 2 dialect [before adjectives in the same way as 多] to what extent; how 火車站離這兒好遠？ Huǒchēzhàn lí zhèr hǎo yuǎn？ How far is the railway station from here? 3 [before indefinite time or numbers] quite 好半天 hǎobàntiān quite a while 好幾個 hǎojǐgè quite a few 好幾天 hǎojǐtiān quite a few days 
verb produce favourable effects 這事可好了他了。 Zhè shì kě hǎo le tā le. This will benefit him. 
auxiliary 1 the better to; in order to; so that 把她的地址告訴我, 我好找她。 Bǎ tā de dìzhǐ gàosu wǒ, wǒ hǎo zhǎo tā. Tell me her address so that I can go and see her. 今兒早點睡, 明兒好早起趕火車。 Jīnr zǎodiǎn shuì, míngr hǎo zǎoqǐ gǎn huǒchē. Let’s turn in early, so as to get up early tomorrow to catch the train. 2 dialect may; can; should 我好進來嗎？ Wǒ hǎo jìnlai ma？ May I come in? 時間不早了, 你好走了。 Shíjiān bù zǎo le, nǐhǎo zǒu le. It’s getting late. You ought to get going.</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="22429952"/><catassign category="IAmMichael"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">友</headword><headword charset="tc">友</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">you3</pron><cantopron type="yyjp" tones="numbers">jau5</cantopron><defn>noun 1 friend 好友 hǎoyǒu good (or great) friend 敵友不分 dí yǒu bù fēn not distinguish between friend and foe 2 companion; company 球友 qiúyǒu companion in playing ball game; playmate 3 member of the same institution, unit, etc. 校友 xiàoyǒu schoolmate; schoolfellow; alumnus 
adjective 1 friendly See 35059456友愛you3ai4友愛 2 of friendly relations 友方 yǒu fāng friendly side</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="35059200"/><catassign category="IAmMichael"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">达</headword><headword charset="tc">達</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">da2</pron><cantopron type="yyjp" tones="numbers">daat6</cantopron><defn>verb 1 extend; be accessible 四通八達 sìtōngbādá extend to all directions; be accessible from all directions 2 reach; attain; amount to 不達目的不罷休 bù dá mùdì bù bàxiū never cease one’s efforts until one achieves the aim; never stop short of goal 糧食平均畝產達千斤。 liángshi píngjūn mǔchǎn dá qiānjīn. The per mu grain yield has reached 500 kilos. 3 understand thoroughly 知書達理 zhīshūdálǐ well-read and highly sensible 4 express; communicate 傳達 chuándá convey; transmit 
adjective literary eminent; distinguished 達官 dáguān high (ranking) official</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="19316480"/><catassign category="IAmMichael"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">见</headword><headword charset="tc">見</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">jian4</pron><cantopron type="yyjp" tones="numbers">gin3</cantopron><defn>noun view; opinion 依我之見 Yī wǒ zhī jiàn in my opinion; to my mind 
verb 1 see; catch sight of 只見一個人影閃過牆角 Zhǐjiàn yī ge rényǐng shǎn guò qiángjiǎo catch sight of sb. turning the corner 從來沒見過這種鳥。 Cónglái méi jiàn guò zhèzhǒng niǎo. I’ve never seen a bird like that before. 2 meet with; be exposed to 見困難就上, 見榮譽就讓 jiàn kùnnan jiùshàng, jiàn róngyù jiùràng dash forward where there are difficulties to overcome and draw back when honours are to be conferred; take difficulty for oneself and leave honours to others 冰見熱就化。 Bīng jiàn rè jiù huà. Ice melts with heat. 這種藥怕見光。 Zhèzhǒng yào pà jiàn guāng. This medicine is not to be exposed to daylight. 見人就獻媚, 誰見誰討厭。 jiàn rén jiù xiànmèi, shuí jiàn shuí tǎoyàn. Those who seek to please everybody please nobody. 3 show evidence of; appear to be 見諸報端 jiàn zhū bàoduān appear in newspapers 見之於行動 jiànzhīyúxíngdòng be translated into action 並不見瘦 bìng bù jiàn shòu not seem to be any thinner 4 refer to; see; vide 見第三十六頁 jiàn dì-sān shíliù yè see page 36 情況已見好轉。 Qíngkuàng yǐ jiàn hǎozhuǎn. The condition is improving. 5 meet; call on; see 待會兒見。 Dāihuir jiàn. See you later. 你見到他了沒有？ Nǐ jiàndào tā le méiyǒu？ Did you meet him? 我不想見他。 Wǒ bù xiǎng jiàn tā. I don’t wish to see him. 她今天下午要來見你。 Tā jīntiān xiàwǔ yào lái jiàn nǐ. She’ll call on you this afternoon. 
verb literary 1 [before a verb to indicate the passive] 見愛 jiàn&apos;ài be loved (or liked); be regarded highly 2 [before a verb in polite requests] See 23814656見告jian4gao4見告</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="23810816"/><catassign category="IAmMichael"/></card><card language="chinese"><entry><headword charset="sc">人</headword><headword charset="tc">人</headword><pron type="hypy" tones="numbers">ren2</pron><cantopron type="yyjp" tones="numbers">jan4</cantopron><defn>noun 1 human being; person; people 活人 huórén living person 人對自然界的認識 Rén duì zìránjiè de rènshi man’s knowledge of nature 團結得像一個人 tuánjié de xiàng yī ge rén (of many people) be united as one 來人了。 lái rén le. Someone has come. or There come some people. 他家有幾口人？ Tā jiā yǒu jǐ kǒu rén？ How many people are there in his family? 屋裡有人嗎？ Wū lǐ yǒurén ma？ Is there anyone inside? 2 adult human being 長大成人 zhǎngdà chéngrén grow up into an adult; be grown to manhood 3 other people; other(s) 他待人誠懇。 Tā dàirén chéngkěn. He’s sincere in his dealings with people. 這個座位有人嗎？ Zhè ge zuòwèi yǒurén ma？ Is this seat occupied? 自己做錯了事, 不應該怪人。 Zìjǐ zuò cuò liǎoshì, bù yīnggāi guàirén. When one has done something wrong one should not blame it on others. 4 [used rhetorically in place of the first personal pronoun, often expressing displeasure] 別小看人！ Bié xiǎokàn rén! Don’t look down on me! 真叫人著急。 Zhēn jiào rén zháojí. It really worries me. 5 person considered as a worker or employee; hand; manpower 人來了嗎？ rén lái le ma? Have they come? 我們這裡正缺人。 Wǒmen zhèlǐ zhèng quē rén. We are short-handed at the moment. 6 physical, psychological, or moral quality or condition of a given individual; personality 他人很好。 Tā rén hěn hǎo. He’s a very nice man. 這兩天我人不太舒服。 Zhè liǎng tiān wǒ rén bù tài shūfu. I haven’t been feeling very well lately. 他人在那兒, 心卻想著別的事。 Tā rén zài nàr, xīn què xiǎngzhe bié de shì. He was there all right, but his mind was elsewhere. 7 everybody; each 人各有所喜。 rén gè yǒusuǒ xǐ. Everyone has his liking. 8 [as a suffix] person of certain places, jobs or properties; person engaging in certain activity 四川人 Sìchuān rén native of Sichuan 文化人 wénhuàrén man of letters; intellectual 音樂人 yīnyuèrén musician; person engaging in music 他是你什麼人？ Tā shì nǐ shénmerén? What is your relation with him? 9 real person; true man; man of integrity 是人就得說人話。 Shì rén jiùděi shuō rén huà. A real man should talk like a real man. 這是人做的事嗎？ Zhè shì rén zuò de shì ma? Can this be the behaviour of a true man?</defn></entry><dictref dictid="PACE" entryid="28962304"/><catassign category="IAmMichael"/></card></cards></plecoflash>